Guide to the Stephen Henry Bronson Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Stephen Henry Bronson collection
1867-1870
Ms Coll 8
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1
(2 boxes)
The Stephen Henry Bronson collection includes autograph correspondence of Dr. Stephen Henry Bronson, while studying abroad in Europe, to his parents, dating from October 1867 to May 1870. There are also typescripts of the correspondence prepared by or for Elizabeth H. Thomson, a member of the faculty of the Department of History of medicine at Yale. One finds in Bronson's letters observations about medicine - in particular anatomy, and academic, civic, cultural and political life in France. There are many references to medicine in Connecticut and in the city of New Haven. The collection also contains a typescript of an article on Bronson by Elizabeth Harriet Thomson, titled "An American Student in Paris," as well as Thomson's notes.
Bronson, Stephen Henry, 1844-1880
Thomson, Elizabeth Harriet, 1907-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Historical Library by Stephen Henry Bronson's niece, Dr. Margaret Bronson Weir, 1973. Transcripts were left by Elizabeth Thomson.
Associated Materials
Stephen Henry Bronson Papers (MS 1282), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Organized in three series: I. Original letters. II Transcripts III Manuscripts on Bronson by Elizabeth H. Thomson.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen Henry Bronson was born in Waterbury, Connecticut on February 18, 1844, the youngest son of Dr. Henry Bronson and Sarah M. (Lathrop) Bronson.. In 1862 he entered the Medical Institution of Yale College from which he graduated in 1866. After graduation he continued his studies in anatomy in Cambridge, Massachusetts and New Haven, Connecticut before entering the Laboratory of Comparative Anatomy attached to the Muséum d'Histoire Naturelle in Paris in the fall of 1867. While in Paris he developed an intimate friendship with Georges Pouchet, and attended lectures in the medical sciences and natural history by Auguste Néalton, Charles Robin, Claude Bernard, J. F. Jarjavary, Armand de Quatrefages, and Henri Milne Edwards. Upon his return from Paris in 1870, Bronson settled in New Haven where he helped to establish the New Haven Dispensary, which opened to the public in 1871. He served as one of its physicians, its secretary, and chief officer. In 1874 he was appointed one of the physicians of New Haven Hospital. Bronson retained these posts until his early death in August, 1880.
Scope and Contents
The documents contained within this collection include original correspondence of Stephen Henry Bronson, while in Europe, to his parents, dating from March 1867 to May 1870, of which both original letters and 20th century typescripts are available. One finds in Bronson's letters observations about medicine - in particular anatomy, and academic, civic, cultural and political life in France. There are many references to medicine in Connecticut and in the city of New Haven. The collection also contains a typescript by Elizabeth Harriet Thomson of an article on Bronson "An American student in Paris,"as well as her notes.
Anatomy, Comparative; Medical education; Medicine -- Connecticut; Medicine -- France; Science; Voyages and travels; Europe -- Description and travel; France -- Description and travel; Great Britain -- Description and travel; Paris (France) -- Description and travel; New Haven (Conn.) -- Description and travel; Bronson, Stephen Henry, 1844-1880; Bronson, Henry, 1804-1893; Bernard, Claude, 1813-1878; Jarjavay, J.-F. (Jean-François), -1868; Milne-Edwards, H. (Henri), 1800-1885; Néalton, Auguste, 1807-1873; Pouchet, G. (Georges), 1833-1894; Quatrefages, A. de (Armand de), 1810-1892; Robin, Ch., 1821-1885; Muséum national d'histoire naturelle (France)
- Letters of Stephen Henry Bronson to his parents, 1867-1870; Series I
  - Original letters, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Orginal letters, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 4-15)
  - Original letters, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 16-27)
  - Original letters, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 28-31)
- Typescripts of letters of Stephen Henry Bronson to his parents, 1867-1870; Series II
  - Transcripts, probably made by Elizabeth Thomson. (Box 1, Folder 32-36)
  - Copies of Transcripts (Box 1, Folder 37-40)
- Manuscripts of articles on Bronson by Elizabeth H. Thomson, after 1973; Series III
  - Elizabeth Thomson, typescript, "An American Student in Paris," 103 pages, after 1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Draft of the above and research notes, after 1973 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous typescripts, after 1973 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Copies of obituaries of Bronson and his father. Includes a typescript of a manuscript obituary attributed to Henry Bronson. (Box 2, Folder 44)